Andrei Panferov

MI RESEARCHEE

Summary _

I am set to graduate this summer with a Bachelor of Applied Mathematics and Physics from the Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, where I am currently ranked in the top 15 out of more than 200 students in my cohort. I studied Machine Learning at the Yandex School of Data Analysis, and I have a keen interest in Natural Language Processing, efficient Deep Learning and Federated Learning. My achievements range from securing a gold medal at the International Physics Olympiad to making significant contributions to the open-source community, as well as acquiring work experience in both industry and academia.

Experience _____

Yandex Research Russia

ML RESEARCH RESIDENT

November 2023 - Present

• Co-authored a first-author paper on *LLM Compression*. Refer to the *Publications* section for more details

KAUST, Optimization and Machine Learning Lab

Research Intern July 2023 - September 2023

- Conducted research, under the supervision of Prof. Peter Richtárik, on distributed optimization, focusing on communication compression
- · Authored a first-author paper on Correlated Quantization. Refer to the Publications section for more details

Eqvilent (High Frequency Trading Fund)

SOFTWARE ENGINEER July 2022 - March 2023

Yandex Russia

ML Engineer Intern (NLP)

March 2022 - July 2022

- Refactored and optimized an LLM inference framework enabling abstract tabular data insertion for efficient map-reduce inference
- Increased test coverage of the *map-reduce* inference interface from 0 to 85% through rigorous unit testing
- Took part in developing a universal LLM benchmarking solution adapting two datasets for it

Terra Quantum AG Russia

RESEARCHER July 2020 - July 2022

- Researched quantum algorithms for business applications
- · Developed an NMR spectra analysis toll, allowing for its use for for quantum computations
- Optimized LLM deployment for chat assistant applications, reducing latency by 40%

Publications

Extreme Compression of Large Language Models via Additive Quantization

Preprint

Saudi Arabia

Remote

VAGE EGIAZARIAN*, *Andrei Panferov**, Denis Kuznedelev, Elias Frantar, Artem Babenko, Dan Alistarh

arxiv.org/abs/2401.06118

Correlated Quantization for Faster Nonconvex Distributed Optimization

Preprint

Andrei Panferov, Yury Demidovich, Ahmad Rammal, Peter Richtárik

arxiv.org/abs/2401.05518

Awards _____

International Physics Olympiad

Israel

GOLD MEDAL

Summer 2019

Education

Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology (MIPT)

Moscow, Russia

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN APPLIED MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2020 - 2024

- Achieved a perfect 5.0/5.0 GPA
- Second minor in Teaching Methods and Pedagogy
- · Working towards my thesis on distributed training of Large Language Models under the supervision of Prof. Alexander Gasnikov

2021 - 2023

- Completed 12 MSc level courses. Specialized in Deep Learning and Natural Language Processing
- Contributed significantly to *Open-Source* (see Open-Source Contributions)
- · Served as a TA for the NLP course. Prepared a seminar on Model Compression, challenged the students to implement GPTQ

Open-Source Contributions _

Tensor_parallel

GITHUB.COM/BLACKSAMOREZ/TENSOR_PARALLEL

- Developed an open-source python library for tensor parallel PyTorch models training and inference tightly integrated with Hugging Face
- Received more than 400 stars on GitHub

LLaMA implementation for transformers

HUGGINGFACE.CO/DOCS/TRANSFORMERS/MAIN/MODEL_DOC/LLAMA#OVERVIEW

• Took part in adapting the LLaMA model for the Huqqing Face transformers library, fixing the positional embedding errors

HuYaLM-100B

HUGGINGFACE.CO/BLACKSAMOREZ/HUYALM-100B-FP16

· Adapted YaLM-100B LLM specifically for Hugging Face transformers, rewriting the officially published Megatron-LM implementation

NLP Bot Project

GITHUB.COM/BLACKSAMOREZ/EBANKO

- Designed an automatic data collection system to extract thousands of dialogues from internet forums, refined the collected data using a pretrained sentiment analysis BERT model and published them it a dataset
- Fine-tuned a GPT-2 model for chatbot purposes on the refined dataset and deployed it as a Telegram bot
- Published an article on Habr (IT social network) about the project, reaching the daily top-1 in the ML section